<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>DigidWorks | Enterprise and Management Software</title>
        <description>DigidWorks provides application development services. We bring software and tech solutions to your business!</description>
        <link>https://digidworks.com/</link>
        <atom:link href="https://digidworks.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 17:31:47 +0300</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2019 17:31:47 +0300</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
        
        <item>
            <title>ERP software for small business [Definition &amp; Benefits]</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of information about ERP software on the web, but most of it is complex and is rarely useful to small and mid-sized businesses.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes the task of deciding whether or not to invest in an ERP all the more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll try to give a more practical answer to the question at hand and I'm going to focus on the more modern web based systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desktop ERP software is still widely used, but I think that a web application is more convenient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;nav class=&quot;mb-5&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h4 id=&quot;table-contents&quot; class=&quot;mb-3&quot;&gt;Table of contents&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;ul class=&quot;nav flex-column&quot;&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#what-is-erp&quot; title=&quot;What is an ERP system?&quot;&gt;
                What is an ERP system?
            &lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#what-are-erp-benefits&quot; title=&quot;What are the benefits of ERP systems?&quot;&gt;
                What are the benefits of ERP systems?
            &lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;ul&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#efficiency&quot; title=&quot;Efficiency&quot;&gt;
                        Efficiency
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#cost-effective&quot; title=&quot;Cost effective&quot;&gt;
                        Cost effective
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#single-source-truth&quot; title=&quot;Single source of truth&quot;&gt;
                        Single source of truth
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#data-security&quot; title=&quot;Data security&quot;&gt;
                        Data security
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#scalability-customization&quot; title=&quot;Scalability &amp; Customization&quot;&gt;
                        Scalability &amp; Customization
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#less-paper&quot; title=&quot;Less paper &amp; greater archiving&quot;&gt;
                        Less paper &amp; greater archiving
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#improved-inventory&quot; title=&quot;Improved inventory management&quot;&gt;
                        Improved inventory management
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#what-are-custom-erp-benefits&quot; title=&quot;What are the benefits of having custom ERP software?&quot;&gt;
                What are the benefits of having custom ERP software?
            &lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#costs&quot; title=&quot;What about costs?&quot;&gt;
                What about costs?
            &lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;ul&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#pricing-models&quot; title=&quot;These are the most common pricing models of off-the-shelf systems.&quot;&gt;
                        These are the most common pricing models of off-the-shelf systems.
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#erp-modules&quot; title=&quot;What are some typical modules and functionalities of an ERP?&quot;&gt;
                What are some typical modules and functionalities of an ERP?
            &lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;ul&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#common-erp-modules&quot; title=&quot;Common modules&quot;&gt;
                        Common modules
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#custom-erp-modules&quot; title=&quot;Customizable modules&quot;&gt;
                        Customizable modules
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#web-vs-desktop-erps&quot; title=&quot;Web based vs. traditional desktop app&quot;&gt;
                Web based vs. traditional desktop app
            &lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#conclusion&quot; title=&quot;Conclusion&quot;&gt;
                Conclusion
            &lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-erp&quot;&gt;What is an ERP system?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERP is abbreviated from Enterprise Resource Planning. To put it another way - this means management of business activities, processes, resources and in some cases - other
    aspects of a company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This type of planning is a complex task and is almost always achieved with the help of a software system. ERP software typically automates big part of the
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Back_office&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;back office&quot;&gt;back office&lt;/a&gt; functions
    of a company. It also gives the user an easy way to do the part that can't (or shouldn't) be automated.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ERP software system is modelled after the specifics of every business. This means that there is no &quot;one size fits all&quot; solution, that will work as good for every
    company out there.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ERP system is like a software representation of the processes in your company. It provides an easy way to enter data, view reports and control your business.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term ERP software is just one category of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.capterra.com/business-management-software/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;business management software&quot;&gt;business management software&lt;/a&gt;,
    but it's often used as a synonym of it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially in smaller businesses an ERP will usually be something like an all in one management suite. It makes more sense like this, because having separate applications
    is counter productive for small companies and more often than not - for bigger ones too.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary: An ERP software is a system that is designed to represent the different aspects for a specific company. It integrates inventory, orders, billing, human resources,
        customers management and everything else that comprises said company. It's used to manage and review data and control employees, resources, etc.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-erp-benefits&quot;&gt;What are the benefits of ERP systems?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;efficiency&quot;&gt;Efficiency&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/erp-software-small-business-definition-benefits/efficiency.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;efficiency&quot;
     title=&quot;efficiency&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERP systems are pretty good at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techopedia.com/definition/671/business-process-automation-bpa&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;business automation&quot;&gt;business automation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally they'll help any business get rid of repetitive tasks and gather data in a less manual manner, thus saving tons of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;cost-effective&quot;&gt;Cost effective&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using an ERP &lt;a href=&quot;/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;How to reduce business costs?&quot;&gt;helps you cut your business expenses&lt;/a&gt;.
    The initial investment for an ERP is big, there's no going about it. But using an integrated solution means you have to support just one single system, not 6. This means you
    spend less on infrastructure, staff, training, etc. If the combined costs of all the systems, it replaces, are bigger than the cost of the ERP system itself, then this is
    another reduction in the overall software expenditure.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;single-source-truth&quot;&gt;Single source of truth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Single source of truth, single point of access, one software to rule them all, call it whatever you want, but that's probably the most important feature of an ERP system.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERPs enforce a unified interface for accessing and modifying data and for controlling your company. You or your employees can't circumvent it, but that's a good thing, because it
    reduces the amount of errors significantly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides, it's way easier to do everything in the same application. You don't have to switch between softwares, accounts or what have you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also that custom report you have to do, that's going to be used in 3 departments is not going to take you a week. It's actually a few clicks away. There's no need to gather data
    from multiple sources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unified tools make planning a lot easier, too. You have all the data about the company at your disposal in the same tool that you're going to use to create the plan. How
    convenient is that?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course all this means better collaboration. Communication is very important in every business. Having your teams working in isolation from one another is counter productive.
    ERP software helps everybody speak the same language.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERPs also make sure the same procedures are used across the whole company. As a result business processes become more standardized and there's less friction between departments.
    This applies to custom developed and to off-the-shelf systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-security&quot;&gt;Data security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/erp-software-small-business-definition-benefits/data-security.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;data security&quot;
     title=&quot;data security&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Businesses are most likely going to see less data errors and discrepancies, when using an ERP. That's because ERPs provide a unified data entry interface and store everything in
    one place.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is great for data security, because it ensures data consistency everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's more to that - data access is also more secure. ERP systems are data repositories, amongst other things. As such they employ advanced data access mechanisms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what are these advanced mechanisms?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical setup would include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Login - credentials based access control is pretty common these days. It works and it gives a good level of security.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Roles and permissions - this is a bit more advanced way to control who can do what in a system. With this data security enhancement the ERP system provides
        the ability to assign roles and permissions to every user. These roles and permissions define the different levels of clearance in the software.
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every business has its own specifics, so there might be cases where additional data security measures are required. These could be custom built in the system.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;scalability-customization&quot;&gt;Scalability &amp; Customization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every business changes. It's important to have tools that are able to change as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most ERP systems are modular by design. You can add and remove different features of the software depending on whether you need them or not.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially a company would get only the modules it needs. You can easily adjust afterwards to reflect any new requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are getting a custom ERP software developed you should make sure the vendors understand that you want a system that is easy to extend.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;less-paper&quot;&gt;Less paper &amp; greater archiving&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using paper in businesses is increasingly frowned upon nowadays. Nobody wants to destroy mother nature or at least nobody wants to look like they are destroying it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whichever your reasoning if you want to use less paper, ERPs are your friend. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This software gives its users the capability to have every document and file at their disposal at all times. What's even better is that digital documents are very easy to tag,
    categorize, search, index, archive, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also get improved storage - a hard disk can contain a whole building worth of documents. Digitally archived documents are very easy to find, unlike their analog
    counterparts.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;improved-inventory&quot;&gt;Improved inventory management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERPs give you the option to assign &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thebalancesmb.com/what-is-a-sku-in-retail-terms-2890158&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;SKU&quot;&gt;codes&lt;/a&gt; to every
    inventory item. What's better is that the current location, status and all other data of the item is easily findable with the software.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more stock you have the more benefits you'll see from inventory management software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-custom-erp-benefits&quot;&gt;What are the benefits of having custom ERP software?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter if you're using an off-the-shelf product or a tailored solution - all ERPs are customized. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The level of customization you're going to get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Niche functionality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;General purpose ERP software is made in such a way, that it's able to serve a very wide variety of businesses and handle their needs. That's because the creators of the software
    want to sell it to as much clients as possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads to systems that are pretty good, when it comes to common tasks, but are lacking in business specific functionality. Implementing every single wish a potential
    customer might have will clutter the system so much, it'll be unusable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Easier to use&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another effect is the added complexity of off-the-shelf applications. When creating a piece of software, that is meant to serve a specific use case, a lot more automations and
    optimizations can be implemented. Ready-made ERP systems usually have more settings and stuff to fill in, their UIs are a bit more complicated and may be intimidating to use at
    the beginning.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course a custom solution will also have the benefit of reflecting the business processes in the specific company it's developed for. With commercial software it's usually
the other way around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Might cost less time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before actually starting to use a commercial ERP there's pretty much always an &quot;integration&quot; process. It is basically deployment, configuration, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is when the customization happens and the ERP gets tuned to meet the more specific business requirements. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What most people don't realize is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This process can take anywhere between 3 months to 2 years.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So contrary to business owners' expectations - there's a considerable time cost to off-the-shelf ERP software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;costs&quot;&gt;What about costs?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spending less is important for every business and an ERP can cost a substantial amount of money to buy and to integrate. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;pricing-models&quot;&gt;These are the most common pricing models of off-the-shelf systems.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;One of the worst (in terms of total expenditure) is the &quot;per month/per user&quot;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techopedia.com/definition/155/software-as-a-service-saas&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;SaaS&quot;&gt;SaaS&lt;/a&gt; pricing model. This makes cost add up very quickly,
        especially for companies, where more employees are going to use the software. I'd say that custom developed solutions pretty much always beat this way of charging clients.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;There's the classical &quot;per month&quot; model, where no matter the users, you are paying a fixed fee every month in order to use the software. This is a
        bit better, but costs still add up pretty quickly.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The &quot;pay once use as long as you want&quot; model is becoming less and less popular these days. Even the variation of it where you have to pay for
        updates and new versions. This is mainly because the developers are making a lot less money this way, but in my opinion this is the fairer way of pricing your products.
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benefits of a custom developed system, when it comes to costs, lie in the fact, that you're only paying for what you're going to be using. This applies to updates and
additional stuff as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;erp-modules&quot;&gt;What are some typical modules and functionalities of an ERP?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/erp-software-small-business-definition-benefits/modules.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Modules&quot;
     title=&quot;Modules&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERPs are modular by design or at least they should be. There are modules that are always present, because every business needs them, and there are more specific modules that can
    be added (or removed) on demand.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;common-erp-modules&quot;&gt;Common modules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Human resources (HR) - In its most basic form this is a module that helps with managing the employees of a company. It provides an easy way to administer
        employee information, like basic data, performance reviews and skill assessments, job descriptions, promotions and so on. It could provide time on task tracking and
        attendance tracking if needed. If a company provides employee trainings or other skill improvement programs it can help with organization.
        It's also used to manage salaries, benefits, travel expenses and other payroll related aspects.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/i/inventory-management.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;Inventory&quot;&gt;Inventory&lt;/a&gt; and
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/s/scm.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;supply chain management (SCM)&quot;&gt;supply chain management (SCM)&lt;/a&gt; - This module deals with stock management and
        logistics. It tracks quantity, quality (you don't want spoiled goods, right?), helps to optimize the flow of products, etc. You can use it to assign unique SKU identifiers
        for easier stock management and access. It keeps track of the
        location of every single item in your company (provided information is entered properly). This is especially useful for businesses with particularly large stock (e.g.
        retail), where things tend to get lost. There are a lot of optimizations that can be made in order to automate information input to this module, thus making things easier.
        Big benefit of the Inventory modules is the reporting it provides. You can get different, specific and very detailed reports about resource expenditure, that make
        identifying problems very easy.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Sales - This module helps with the management of the typical sales process. It deals with inquiries, quotations, orders, invoicing or billing,
        dispatching goods, etc. It also provides access to advanced reports on sales data, that can be used in business planning.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Purchases - This module helps with the management of the process of purchasing goods, needed by the company. It helps with vendor and price list
        management, updating stock and in general with the whole process of buying products. This module gives access to advanced reporting, that can provide insights about the way
        a company spends money.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Customer relationship management (CRM) - This module gathers all the customer related data in one place. It helps with managing basic data like customer
        contacts and details and integrates sales, support and feedback data. It also keeps history of all interactions with a client. This module serves as a databank for all
        customer facing employees, so that they can make informed decisions and provide the best customer experience possible.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Teams and projects - These modules help with managing employees, projects and the whole work process. They assist with time management, task management,
        issue management, etc. The reports they provide can be used to assess efficiency, employee's and team's skill and to create better time estimates for future projects.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Documents - This module is used to manage different company documents. The archiving capabilities are a huge advantage over traditional ways of storing
        and searching documents.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Production - This module can be in both categories, because in some cases there's a lot of room for customization. The general purpose features of it
        include:
        &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Planning for material requirements&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Planning for human resource requirements&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Expenditure reports&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Business intelligence (BI) - This module gathers data from the whole database of the ERP (and sometimes from external sources as well) in order to
        generate reports for the upper-level executives in the company. It's sole purpose is to help company management with data and insights.
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;custom-erp-modules&quot;&gt;Customizable modules&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possibilities here are unlimited. These modules depend solely on the requirements of the business acquiring the ERP system. I'll list some of the custom modules
    we've developed for our customers, but this is in no way an exhaustive list.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Production - we already have that one in the common modules section. I'm adding it here, because production is different in every enterprise and there's
        a lot of room for customization. Production module for a smart farm will be very different from a production module for a cake factory.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Calendar - This is more of an organizational module, to help with proper timing and scheduling. There could be subtle differences between Calendars for
        different departments.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Patients - This is a module for clinics and hospitals. It's used to manage every aspect of the patient's stay, condition, feedback and so on. It can also
        keep an archive of information and generate detailed statistics. There will be differences from one establishment to another.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Doctors/Surgeons/Nurses - Another module used in clinic and hospital ERPs. It helps with management of specialized staff, proper scheduling, time
        tracking, etc.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Space scheduling - This module is used by enterprises that have a lot of spaces used by 3rd parties. It could be rooms in hospitals and hotels or sports
        facilities in companies that provide them. It makes sure there are no overlaps and helps with using the facilities as close to their full capacity as possible.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Cleaning and maintenance - This is used to manage the cleaning and maintenance cycles of different facilities. It can provide monitoring, mark for clean
        up or inspection and other specific functionalities.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Drivers - This is a module that provides real-time information and management of a company's drivers. Some optional features include real-time messaging,
        advanced reporting and others.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Vehicles - There's a lot of room for customization in this one. It could be a simple management module, with data about the vehicles and their status. It
        could provide real-time monitoring, data about the way vehicles are being used, technical inspection and insurance calendars and alarms, etc.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Alerts, monitoring - Custom alerts and monitoring are nothing new. But they are different for every enterprise. Alerts module helps the users of an ERP
        system not to miss important events. Detailed monitoring helps with early problem identification and prevention.
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;web-vs-desktop-erps&quot;&gt;Web based vs. traditional desktop app&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/erp-software-small-business-definition-benefits/web-vs-desktop.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Web vs. desktop&quot;
     title=&quot;Web vs. desktop&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically for the case of ERP software I think that web based applications are better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Development for web applications is usually a bit cheaper and faster, which is always a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's much easy to access them from everywhere. You just need a browser and an internet connection. This sounds a lot better, compared to having to install a huge desktop
    program.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security is always a concern, but this applies to both web and desktop software. Since most likely both will need to communicate over a network with different resources (e.g.
    database), they are both vulnerable to attacks. So it's important to make sure your vendor will implement proper security.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deployment, configuration and updates are fairly easier on web apps. You only do it on a single centralized machine. With desktop apps you have to make sure, that everybody will
    install the update properly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ERP software is an important tool for running a business. It provides its users with advanced management and monitoring capabilities for general purpose and business specific
    tasks.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the costs of integrating an ERP system can be considerable, the benefits gained in the form of optimization of business processes, error reduction and time saved
    definitely outweigh them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter the size of the company, a good ERP software suite will surely help a lot.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
            <link>https://digidworks.com/erp-software-small-business-definition-benefits</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://digidworks.com/erp-software-small-business-definition-benefits</guid>
            
            <category>ERP</category>
            
            <category>Software</category>
            
            <category>Small business</category>
            
            <category>Medium business</category>
            
            <category>Management</category>
            
            
            <category>product-descriptions</category>
            
            <category>enterprise</category>
            
            <category>management</category>
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>How to cut business costs? [Ultimate guide]</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my advanced guide on how to cut business costs without sacrificing quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to writing this I've done quite a lot of research and I've also included some real-life examples from my
    experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I've tried to be very comprehensive. This is the reason why this turned out to be 6000+ words post.
    Feel free to use the &lt;a href=&quot;#table-contents&quot; title=&quot;Table of Contents&quot;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/a&gt; below
    to skip to the parts that interest you the most.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've intentionally avoided some cost reduction techniques, because in the end they'll bring more harm than good. I'll
    add them to the &lt;a href=&quot;#bad-cost-cutting&quot; title=&quot;There are bad ways to cut costs&quot;&gt;Bad cost cutting&lt;/a&gt; section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we begin I have to make 1 thing clear:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It will be best to implement these strategies before you actually need to.&lt;/strong&gt; You should look at this article more as a
    business optimisation guide, that focuses on reducing unnecessary costs, rather
    than a salvage my company kind of guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main idea is to achieve effective, sustainable, long-term cost reduction for your company, without sacrificing
    any of the quality or value you provide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I'm trying to say is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If your revenue is low and your reserves are non-existent, then it's probably a bit late.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons for this are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It's better to never reach a moment when your business actually needs to reduce expenditure in order to stay
        afloat. This makes you vulnerable to making bad decisions.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;The best ways to reduce costs usually require an upfront investment. Which is hard to do, when you don't have
        enough money.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It takes time to see the positive effects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the best part about this approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you do this right, you're probably going to increase the overall effectiveness of your business, which should be
        one of the main goals for every businessman.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;nav class=&quot;mb-5&quot;&gt;
    &lt;h4 id=&quot;table-contents&quot; class=&quot;mb-3&quot;&gt;Table of contents&lt;/h4&gt;
    &lt;ul class=&quot;nav flex-column&quot;&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#general-tips&quot; title=&quot;The foundations of cost saving&quot;&gt;
                The foundations of cost saving
            &lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;ul&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#monitor-analyze-optimize&quot; title=&quot;Monitor, analyze, optimize&quot;&gt;
                        Monitor, analyze, optimize
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#planning&quot; title=&quot;Planning and budgeting&quot;&gt;
                        Planning and budgeting
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#automation&quot; title=&quot;Automate as much as possible&quot;&gt;
                        Automate as much as possible
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#outsourcing&quot; title=&quot;Outsource everything you can&quot;&gt;
                        Outsource everything you can
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#operational-costs&quot; title=&quot;Cut operational costs&quot;&gt;
                Cut operational costs
            &lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;ul&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#erp-business-management-software&quot; title=&quot;Use management software to help reduce costs&quot;&gt;
                        Use management software to help reduce costs
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#fixed-assets&quot; title=&quot;Be efficient with your fixed assets&quot;&gt;
                        Be efficient with your fixed assets
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#coworking&quot; title=&quot;Reduce office expenses&quot;&gt;
                        Reduce office expenses
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#meetings&quot; title=&quot;Meetings are time wasters&quot;&gt;
                        Meetings are time wasters
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#equipment&quot; title=&quot;Lower equipment spending&quot;&gt;
                        Lower equipment spending
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#oss&quot; title=&quot;Use free or open source software&quot;&gt;
                        Use free or open source software
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#recurring-payments&quot; title=&quot;Try to avoid recurring payments&quot;&gt;
                        Try to avoid recurring payments
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#upgrade&quot; title=&quot;Upgrade&quot;&gt;
                        Upgrade
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#employee-monitoring&quot; title=&quot;Employee monitoring&quot;&gt;
                        Employee monitoring
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#reward-value&quot; title=&quot;Reward value given to the company&quot;&gt;
                        Reward value given to the company
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#working-hours&quot; title=&quot;Reduce working hours&quot;&gt;
                        Reduce working hours
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#supplies&quot; title=&quot;Reduce supply expenditure&quot;&gt;
                        Reduce supply expenditure
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#digital&quot; title=&quot;Go digital&quot;&gt;
                        Go digital
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#production-costs&quot; title=&quot;Cut production costs&quot;&gt;
                        Cut production costs
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#vehicles&quot; title=&quot;Lower vehicle expenses&quot;&gt;
                        Lower vehicle expenses
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#electric&quot; title=&quot;Save on the electric bill&quot;&gt;
                        Save on the electric bill
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#inventory&quot; title=&quot;Don't keep excess inventory&quot;&gt;
                        Don't keep excess inventory
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#financial&quot; title=&quot;Financial cost saving&quot;&gt;
                Financial cost saving
            &lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;ul&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#fintech&quot; title=&quot;Use fintech services&quot;&gt;
                        Use fintech services
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#unneeded-services&quot; title=&quot;You might not need this&quot;&gt;
                        You might not need this
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
                &lt;li&gt;
                    &lt;a href=&quot;#late-payments&quot; title=&quot;Avoid late payments&quot;&gt;
                        Avoid late payments
                    &lt;/a&gt;
                &lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#marketing&quot; title=&quot;Marketing&quot;&gt;
                Marketing
            &lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#bad-cost-cutting&quot; title=&quot;Bad cost cutting&quot;&gt;
                Bad cost cutting
            &lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;
            &lt;a href=&quot;#conclusion&quot; title=&quot;Conclusion&quot;&gt;
                Conclusion
            &lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we are past the disclaimer let's dive right in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;general-tips&quot;&gt;General tips for sustainable business cost reduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;monitor-analyze-optimize&quot;&gt;Monitor, analyze, optimize.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/monitor-analyze-optimize.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Always monitor, analyze and optimize your business&quot;
     title=&quot;Always monitor, analyze and optimize your business&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know it sounds a little bit generic, but this is probably &lt;em&gt;the most important and effective thing anybody can do in
    their efforts to reduce business expenditure, increase revenue and get the maximum &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/r/returnoninvestment.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;return
            for your investments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the reason why different business intelligence and management systems are so wide spread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They can give you invaluable insights about where you can easily make changes, that will be very profitable
        and will help you identify hidden blockages and &quot;leaks&quot;.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My clients have shared all kinds of different findings with me, gathered with the help of their
    &lt;a href=&quot;/erp-software-small-business-definition-benefits&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;ERP software definition for small to medium businesses&quot;&gt;ERPs&lt;/a&gt;
    and
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://searchbusinessanalytics.techtarget.com/definition/business-intelligence-BI&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;
       rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;What is business intelligence&quot;&gt;business intelligence&lt;/a&gt; systems.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From small things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;One department using a few times more office supplies than the others, because employees use them for personal
        stuff
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Workers coming systematically too late to work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To bigger things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Some drivers driving way more carelessly than others and thus causing cars to break down faster&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Drivers running personal errands and thus increasing fuel expenditure significantly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To some, who did major shifts, like changing their whole process, because they saw how this will
help them reduce operating expenses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;planning&quot;&gt;Planning and budgeting.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/planning-budgeting.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Planning and budgeting are important for your business&quot;
     title=&quot;Planning and budgeting are important for your business&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounds more complicated than it really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Business planning is essential to every company, no matter the size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gives you well defined goals to pursue and the steps to accomplish them.
    &lt;strong&gt;It keeps you focused on what's important for growth,
        improving organization and reducing time and money wasted.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how you do it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Set a goal you want your business to achieve.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Determine the steps that you need to take to reach that goal.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Allocate the needed resources for each step.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Start executing the steps.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Analyze the results and eventually adjust course if they are not the expected ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A simple rule of thumb:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can't figure out how to do a certain step or how to budget for it - break it down into smaller steps.
If you accomplish the smaller steps, you have accomplished the big one as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good business planning or management software can help a lot with that. The detailed statistics provided by
    such tools are great for planning. You'll be able to examine closely how your business functioned in
    previous periods, keeping everything on track.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;automation&quot;&gt;Automate as much as possible.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/automate.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Automate to reduce expenses&quot;
     title=&quot;Automate to reduce expenses&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of businesses struggle with that. Either because they don't want to invest in it, thinking it won't
    benefit them, or because they are afraid something will go wrong and believe
    they are perfectly fine the way they are.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Even if you are OK at the moment it doesn't mean you shouldn't try to improve.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the biggest companies in the world are successfully cutting costs with automation. &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2018/10/30/alibaba-cainiao-chinas-biggest-robot-warehouse-for-singles-day.html&quot;
        target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;At &quot;Alibaba&quot; they use robots in their warehouses&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://blogs.wsj.com/japanrealtime/2015/08/21/fully-automated-lettuce-factory-to-open-in-japan/&quot;
        target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;&quot;Spread&quot; uses robotics to farm lettuce&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/adidas-manufacturing-idUSL8N13X3CQ20151209&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;
        rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;&quot;Adidas&quot; uses robots to make running shoes&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many more examples, just check out what the guys at
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bostondynamics.com/&quot; title=&quot;Boston Dynamics&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;
       rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Boston Dynamics&lt;/a&gt; are doing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 my-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe class=&quot;embed-responsive-item&quot; data-src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/5iV_hB08Uns&quot;
            allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows us that saving with automation works and it works really well. Otherwise
    nobody would have put the time and effort to research and create fully automated
    manufacturing facilities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter if you can do it on this scale or not.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can always use the help of computers to automate some
            of the smaller things in your business and reduce your expenses this way.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With recent advances a lot of stuff that was pretty hard to do in the past is easily achievable today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some examples, just to get you started:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You can automate communication to get custom alerts, whenever something you care about happens. E.g.
    when a server is down, when you receive comment on your blogs, whenever somebody tries to access resources without
    proper authorization, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You can automate sending different &quot;Thank you&quot; messages or even client onboarding. More advanced features are
        made available from the different customer support tools out there.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You can automate price estimates, orders, invoices, billing, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;outsourcing&quot;&gt;Outsource everything you can.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/outsource.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Outsourcing can save a lot of money and hassle&quot;
     title=&quot;Outsourcing can save a lot of money and hassle&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nowadays there's a company for everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You don't want to deal with HR?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a company that does this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You don't want to deal with sales?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No problem!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marketing? Advertising? Accounting?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In general outsourcing everything that is not your forte is the way to go.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiring personnel is expensive and it's not worth it outside your core activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You'll waste a lot of time finding the right candidate. The lack of experience can lead to serious problems and
    expenses and since you aren't a pro yourself you can't really train somebody. You can
    just hope for the best, which isn't the best strategy for anything.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is the option to hire a trainer to train your staff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that's even worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of paying somebody to do the task at hand, you'll be paying somebody to teach you (or your employees)
    how to do it. And you'll be paying premium, because trainers usually aren't cheap.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides I'm far from convinced that when the training is done the trainees will be as good at the task at hand as the
    trainer is.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiring a highly specialized company will give you all the benefits and none of the problems. You get a lot of
    experience, skills, contacts, tools, knowledge, know-how, etc. that you would otherwise
    have to spend a fortune on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;More importantly you get a partner, that is highly motivated to help you, because that's their business.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your only concern is probably going to be management. But provided you have the right management software you should
    be fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;operational-costs&quot;&gt;Reduce operating expenses in business.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;erp-business-management-software&quot;&gt;Use ERP or other management software.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's a reason why these tools are so widely adopted in businesses over the globe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They work!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When it comes to cost reduction seeing data organised in charts and tables is invaluable.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also get the benefit of having everything centralized. This way finding information
    (e.g. supplier details, products pricing, etc.) is much faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every ERP can generate customized reports. Throwing out irrelevant data from a report makes working with it more
    productive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an ERP you will have the ultimate stock control. You'll be able to identify hidden problems with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After integrating an ERP and doing some A/B testing one of my clients reported, that buying a different brand of
        screwdriver bits resulted in spending 20% less for bits and using them 15% longer on average.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See how you can save easily on smaller things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, next one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;fixed-assets&quot;&gt;Use your fixed assets as efficiently as you can.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/efficient-assets.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Using fixed assets efficiently can save money&quot;
     title=&quot;Using fixed assets efficiently can save money&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It could be office space, production real estate, big machinery, etc. but it should be used to its fullest potential.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don't mean using your meeting rooms twice a week or your multi spindle drilling machine 7 times a month. You have
    to be putting your assets to work as close to 100% of the time as you can get.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a couple of ways to do it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Some of your office spaces can have two functions. Your meeting room can be your break room or you can combine
        storage and printing.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You can rent out spaces you're currently not using.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You can offer usage of your assets as a service. Smaller companies, DIYers, handymen, etc. that don't have access to
            such big machines will gladly use that.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's of course one problem that can quickly arise:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad scheduling.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be easily remedied with a good management or scheduling software. This way you'll always be in control of
    your schedules and there won't be any mix-ups.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you own a sports facility, then good scheduling is crucial for you. You need it in order to optimize your usage of
    the playgrounds and maximize the time in which you're making money out of them, thus reducing loses.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are a bit more enthusiastic about automation in a lot of cases you can integrate a great deal of
    interconnected devices and an admin dashboard for them. This way you will be able to control your schedules and the
    devices from the same application. &lt;em&gt;This is a real time and money saver&lt;/em&gt; - if we go back to the sports facility
    example turning the lights and music off and locking a room could be happening with a mouse click.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My next tip is better suited for smaller businesses (of course it'll work well for medium sized companies as well):
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;coworking&quot;&gt;Use coworking office spaces or even work fully remotely.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this can save a substantial amount of cash. &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/larryalton/2017/05/09/why-more-millennials-are-flocking-to-shared-office-spaces/&quot;
        target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Shared
        offices are cheaper&lt;/a&gt; in comparison to renting or buying a traditional office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also you get the added benefit of somebody taking care of utilities, maintenance, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to expand this further and if your business allows it - you can offer telecommuting or even go the fully
    remote (or office-free) way. A lot of companies are doing this and
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/laurashin/2017/01/31/work-from-home-in-2017-the-top-100-companies-offering-remote-jobs/&quot;
       target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;the trend is going up&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's good for office morale and for your wallet. Working remotely usually means happier employees, which is always a
    good thing. But it'll also potentially save you from utility costs (like
    electricity, water, internet, etc.) and office space.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides reducing costs, this way of working has other benefits. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ohio.edu/&quot;  target=&quot;_blank&quot;
                                                                          rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;University of
        Ohio&lt;/a&gt; created a
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinemasters.ohio.edu/blog/how-telecommuting-can-save-businesses-money/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;
       rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;very nice article and infographic on the topic&lt;/a&gt;, which you can check out here:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(After that I'm talking about a potential issue with remote work and how to solve it)&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style=&quot;clear:both;margin-bottom:20px;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinemasters.ohio.edu/blog/how-telecommuting-can-save-businesses-money/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;
       rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
        &lt;img data-src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/utep-uploads/wp-content/uploads/sparkle-box/2018/03/22163308/telecommuting-can-save-businesses-money-image.jpg&quot;
             alt=&quot;Telecommuting Can Save Businesses Money infographic&quot; style=&quot;max-width:100%;&quot;/&gt;
    &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The potential issue I mentioned is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Management.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing a team remotely can be a challenge. You have to figure out ways of communication (don't forget
    that you might have personnel in different time zones), task assignments, file sharing, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience shows that technology can help a lot for this. You have different issue tracking systems like: &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://www.atlassian.com/software/jira&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;JIRA&lt;/a&gt;,
    &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://asana.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Asana&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://trello.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Trello&lt;/a&gt;. Everybody is using
    messaging apps nowadays, so I'm only going to mention Skype, Slack and &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://hangouts.google.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Google Hangouts&lt;/a&gt;
    as the most popular ones. File sharing is also pretty easy: &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;DropBox&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://www.google.com/drive/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt; are
    just 2 of the many alternatives you can use.

    In the end it all comes down to preference, but the more things you can do with one app and the more it's suited for
    your specific needs - the better. You will easily save time and headaches if you
    can consolidate your management efforts in as little applications as possible or in a single customized one.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;meetings&quot;&gt;Meetings are time wasters.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/meetings-waste-time.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Most meetings waste valuable time&quot;
     title=&quot;Most meetings waste valuable time&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, that's right, unless you're actually making key decisions or making money &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/jeff-haden/why-99-percent-of-all-meetings-are-a-complete-wast.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;
        rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;you're wasting time&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often people tend to steer off of the agenda, talk about unrelated stuff and also forget about things they talked
    about later.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can easily drop most of the meetings if you use some kind of &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_project_management_software&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;
        team tracking, organization and management app&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way you will gain the following benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You will have history of everything that has been &quot;said&quot; on the given issue/task/theme/etc.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;It'll be a lot easier to assign tasks and have people do them.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You can benefit from the so called &quot;agile&quot; methodologies for team management.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;If somebody starts working on a given issue later they'll be able to easily follow everything that was
        discussed prior to them joining.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You don't have to do recaps and waste more time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you have remote workforce you'll save even more from travel expenses.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;equipment&quot;&gt;Be smart about equipment.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/smart-equipment.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Don't always buy new and expensive stuff&quot;
     title=&quot;Don't always buy new and expensive stuff&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can always buy the newest and best of everything, but you also might not need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you can buy second hand or refurbished stuff - do it, it's cheaper and you often get some remaining
    warranty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to buy a crane a used one is usually a much better choice. It'll cost a lot less (depending on the type
    of crane), but more importantly - &lt;em&gt;it should have a service history, with all the maintenance and repairs&lt;/em&gt;. This
    way you can easily determine the condition of the machine and make educated decision on whether or not it's a good
    purchase.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also rent equipment if you only use it once in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can rent out your own stuff when you don't need it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An advice from me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don't waste money on stuff you don't really need.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll talk more about this later in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;oss&quot;&gt;Use free or open source software.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a free alternative to pretty much any computer program you might be using. You can save a lot of money if you
    start using these.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There's another added benefit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can make donations to the products you like the most whenever the right moment comes. This way you'll be making
    the world a better place and you also might get a mention on the product's
    sponsors page.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source and free software has changed a lot since the days it was almost unusable (or non existent).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have free operating systems (Linux), that work quite well and are becoming more and more user-friendly. There are
    free office suites, creativity apps, management apps, accounting software, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It's a good practice to check for a free alternative whenever you consider buying a license, it might save
        you a lot!&lt;/strong&gt; In some cases it might be even better than the paid alternative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can give an example with myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This website is hosted for free on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot; title=&quot;GitHub Pages&quot;
                                         target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;, using free caching from
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudflare.com/&quot; title=&quot;Cloudflare&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;cloudflare&lt;/a&gt;. I'm using the
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot; title=&quot;Jekyll - Free static blog system&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;free blogging platform jekyll&lt;/a&gt;
    to generate it and I'm writing this post for free in my google docs, running on my
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.archlinux.org/&quot; title=&quot;Arch Linux&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;free Arch Linux operating system&lt;/a&gt;. I'm
    editing images in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gimp.org/&quot; title=&quot;GNU image manipulation program&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;GIMP&lt;/a&gt;,
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://krita.org/&quot; title=&quot;Professional FREE and open source painting program&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Krita&lt;/a&gt;
    or &lt;a href=&quot;https://inkscape.org/&quot; title=&quot;Professional vector graphics editor &quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Inkscape&lt;/a&gt;
    which are all free.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, next one is connected to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;website&quot;&gt;Website.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I give you the tips I must say this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nowadays it's important for &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; business to have a website.&lt;/strong&gt; Don't skimp on the cost
of a good website. It doesn't matter if you'll be investing in digital marketing or not. If somebody tries to look you
up you must show up in the results, otherwise you risk losing a client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for how to save from a business website, here are a few pointers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        In most of the cases you don't really need a custom made
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Content_management_system&quot; title=&quot;What's a CMS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;CMS&lt;/a&gt;.
        You can use wordpress, joomla, drupal or even jekyll if you're OK with a more technical solution (as I
        mentioned in the previous section - that's the one I'm using).
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        Be very careful where you get your domain name from. There are some domain registrars, who have hidden fees,
        really bad terms and conditions, bad support, etc. &lt;strong&gt;Do your research before buying, to save some money.
        &lt;/strong&gt;
        In my research on the topic done in 2019 I gathered positive and negative feedback of people from different
        forums and I came to the conclusion that Google, CloudFlare, NameSilo and PorkBun are OK. Currently I'm using
        CloudFlare.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        Be really careful about hosting too. Again you should check different reviews (avoid the paid PR reviews,
        check reddit, forums, etc.). Price is important but also is performance and extras.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
        If you want to save some cash from the design of your website you can always buy one from the different website
        template marketplaces like TemplateMonster. It's much cheaper this way, but you might end up with pretty much
        the same website as somebody else.
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, time to move to the next one and this is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;recurring-payments&quot;&gt;Try to avoid recurring payments. &lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/recurring-payments.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Avoiding recurring payments can save a lot&quot;
     title=&quot;Avoiding recurring payments can save a lot&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Renting has one big benefit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It's easy and convenient.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once or twice a month you need a bus to drive your workers somewhere or maybe a super powerful computer to render the
    video clip you made. It could also be power tools if you use wider range of
    them and you don't want to invest.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Renting is viable solution to such problems. But these costs quickly add up and sometimes it makes more sense to just
    buy the thing you need.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just do a quick calculation of your renting costs for let's say 2 years versus the cost of just buying the thing. If
    renting is equal or higher - you know what to do.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it's not - the margin should be quite big for buying not to be the better option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll give you another interesting example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software licenses.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More and more companies are providing their software as a service, not as a product. It's quite popular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this actually means is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to make recurring payments monthly or yearly in order to have the most recent version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's also this new trend emerging in which you have to pay also per user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasoning behind this payment model is that you are always getting the latest and greatest version of the
    software and that each user needs more resources provisioned on the provider's servers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only problem is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The benefits of always being on the bleeding edge of technology are at best debatable for most.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the per user cost - it's often caused by the fact that the provider is trying to serve &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C10k_problem&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;a lot of clients at the same time&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now a quick calculation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say you're paying for a small app (Slack is about $7 per month, per user). If you have 100 employees, that
    ammounts to $700 per month, for just one tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for the first year it's $8400. Then if you add the second it's $16 800. And so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
   &lt;strong&gt;That can cover the costs of developing a simpler enterprise chat application, that will still do the
       job for you.&lt;/strong&gt; Provided you don't need every single feature of Slack.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see how this can easily amount to piles of money going out of your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other problems as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You get functionality you don't need, but you're paying for it&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You don't get the functionality you actually need, although you're paying for it&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Support usually isn't that great, performance may be pretty bad, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you can do about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Talk to a development agency and ask them to create something that will suit your needs.&lt;/em&gt;
    The initial costs will be higher, but having no recurring licence payments will
    quickly catch up. Afterwards you only pay when you need additional stuff developed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;upgrade&quot;&gt;Upgrade.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your software, your hardware, your tools, your appliances, your offices, everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's why:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;By upgrading old equipment you're gaining better performance.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More often than not a performance boost results in time and money savings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course this should be taken with a grain of salt, because not every upgrade is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are a software company, so as expected we work on computers to create, well... software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably most people think that because computers are our main tool, we are always working on cutting edge tech.
    &lt;strong&gt;And they are wrong.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We haven't upgraded our CPUs for the last 4 years, because the performance gain for the things we do would be less
    than 5%. But we do use high-end SSDs &lt;strong&gt;despite their high cost, because the gain is
        significant.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do use a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rolling_release&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;rolling-release&lt;/a&gt;
    linux operating system (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.archlinux.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Arch Linux&lt;/a&gt;) in
    order to always have up-to-date software, again because we need this and it's very beneficial to us.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you own a restaurant - a new high-end coffee maker will be better than an old one - it'll work faster, it'll
    make better coffee and it'll break down less often.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're into car repairs better tools means better and faster repairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you're a carpenter having new and powerful drill and table saw is going to make things easier for you, which again
    means reducing overall costs.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same applies for pretty much every business, so don't be afraid to invest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just be smart about it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don't hesitate to buy the things that will make you money, but avoid unnecessary purchases.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;employee-monitoring&quot;&gt;Employee monitoring.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/employee-monitoring.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;It's important to know the strengths and weaknesses of your employees&quot;
     title=&quot;It's important to know the strengths and weaknesses of your employees&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me make one thing clear:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody likes to be watched over like it's 1984.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But unobtrusive monitoring of your employees' activity has its benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefit #1:&lt;/strong&gt; You will find the slackers. People that come way too late to work or that take way too long lunch breaks
    regularly. What you do with them depends on a lot of things and is out of the
    scope of this post.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Benefit #2:&lt;/strong&gt; You will understand what the strengths and the weaknesses of your employees are. You'll find who are the
    employees that give you the most value. More importantly - over time you'll be
    able to use your employees' skills more efficiently, because you'll know what they are good at.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A management application can help a lot with that. You can check when employees come to the office, when they go to
    and return from breaks and when they leave the office. You can also check the
    time it takes somebody to complete a task and privately rate if they did a good job or not.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing and task distribution becomes way easier, when you have the right data. &lt;strong&gt;Effective management
        is one of the best ways to reduce costs in business.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;reward-value&quot;&gt;Reward value given to the company.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encourage your employees to give value to the company. &lt;em&gt;Rewarding for time spent in the workplace is kind of old
        school and it's not the most efficient tactic.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've all seen (either on TV or in the real life) this one employee that constantly plays games while &quot;working&quot;.
    Over time this can add up to a lot of money wasted.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it's a good idea to encourage employees to give value to the company. You can do that by organising trainings,
    giving a bonus for a job well done, have flexible working hours, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course you should always monitor and evaluate performance, so that you'll have statistics and history of what
    happened.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all implementing this strategy should reduce operational costs, but more importantly - it should also
    increase employee output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;working-hours&quot;&gt;Reduce working hours.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/reduce-working-hours.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Reducing working hours has potential benefits&quot;
     title=&quot;Reducing working hours has potential benefits&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is a bit counter intuitive and controversial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just bare with me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent studies report that &lt;a href=&quot;https://phys.org/news/2018-07-four-day-weeks-days.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;
                                 rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;reduced working hours
        actually pay off&lt;/a&gt; and that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vouchercloud.com/resources/office-worker-productivity&quot;
                                         target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;the
        average worker is clocking in no more than 3-4 hours&lt;/a&gt;. This applies especially to creative activities or
    ones that involve a lot of thinking. So if your type of business allows it, you could reduce working hours a bit.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way you will gain from the increased productivity and save from office costs. &lt;strong&gt;Also don't forget the happiness
        factor.&lt;/strong&gt; Everybody at the office will love you for the improved work-life balance.
&lt;em&gt;Happy employees are much more likely to bring greater value to your company than unhappy ones.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;supplies&quot;&gt;Reduce supply expenditure.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can save a lot of money for some businesses like food joints, carpenters, car repair shops, construction businesses, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can monitor closely the usage of materials and try to optimize it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identifying leaks is important&lt;/strong&gt; - there
    could be somebody &quot;borrowing&quot; stuff from you, an employee working very inefficiently with some material or
    something else that's creating excess usage of supplies, that remains hidden.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finding these issues you should fix them and make sure they are less likely to happen again in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What's more important:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You should always check the most recent price lists of suppliers&lt;/strong&gt;, because there could be significant differences with
    the price you're getting from your current supplier.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find out that you're being charged more you can either switch or let your current supplier know about it and
    ask for a discount.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automating this process can make your life a lot easier, because receiving a notification whenever a lower price
    appears is much more efficient and time saving than having to go through a bunch of
    price lists every week.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;digital&quot;&gt;Go digital as much as you can.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Printing is expensive, archiving stuff on paper even more so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since computers are a big part of our lives you can save a buck if you decide to &lt;strong&gt;drop printing and paper
        altogether.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another benefit of digitalisation is that it's much more convenient - sending an email is a lot faster than printing
    something and sending it over conventional mail.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also if you're going the digital route, archived documents can be indexed and then easily searched for the tiniest
    bit of information when you need it. &lt;strong&gt;This is way cheaper than paying for physical document storage
        and much more efficient if you're trying to find some offer from ten years ago.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    If phone calls are a significant part of your business again you can benefit from digital services. Landlines
    usually cost more than &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voice_over_IP&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;
                              rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;VoIP&lt;/a&gt; and have worse quality.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A lot of management can be digitalised as well&lt;/strong&gt;. This does not lead directly to cost cutting, but it
    would improve efficiency a lot and will reduce wasted time, errors and other different misunderstandings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example integrating a good team management system can be incredibly beneficial. What you get is a central
    repository with all projects, all the tasks of all employees (and your own if you want to), etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everybody sees only the things they need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This way you won't have employees forgetting what they had to do.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good user interface helps a lot because it lets everybody use the software, but more importantly it provides
    ease of use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;searching and grouping of tasks&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;color coding&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;adding different types of media&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;many more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also get automatic &quot;deadlines&quot;, reminders and alerts for your tasks. Also task queuing can be automated. It's
    determined either by creation order or by task &quot;weight&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course if you're building a custom team or a whole business management suite you can add whatever
    functionality you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the long run this will substantially reduce wasted money and time &lt;strong&gt;(so it's a good cost cutter)&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course you don't have to stop here, using technology can help in a lot of aspects of your business. &lt;strong&gt;You've
    probably noticed that most of the problems mentioned in this article have a working solution using computers and
    software.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;production-costs&quot;&gt;Cut production costs.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/cut-production-costs.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;How to reduce production costs&quot;
     title=&quot;How to reduce production costs&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the process of creating a material product a lot of businesses have leftovers, cut-outs, scraps and any other kind
    of stuff that goes to waste in the end.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of cost saving measures you can take to reduce waste and losses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Recycling is sometimes an option, although it's kind of a last resort one.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You can use some simple design tool, CAD software or some custom application to optimize the way you use
        materials. Let's say you're in the carpentry business and you're using
        chipboard. An app can create optimized cutting diagram that will save you material and therefore money.
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;You can sell leftovers. There are &lt;a
            href=&quot;http://fortune.com/2015/04/16/could-these-apps-solve-americas-huge-food-waste-problem/&quot;
            target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;a
            ton of initiatives out there for restaurants, cafes and all other types of food joints trying to reduce
            food waste&lt;/a&gt;. Some of them sell the food at lower prices at the end of the day, others just give it away.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In some cases good inventory and production management can help. You can use an application that will help you
        determine the optimal quantities you should buy of each product and
        the optimal quantities you should produce. This way much less products will go bad, remain unsold, etc. reducing
        your overall expenditure significantly.
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;vehicles&quot;&gt;Lower vehicle expenses.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/vehicle-costs.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;Vehicles cost a lot&quot;
     title=&quot;Vehicles cost a lot&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vehicles are a rather big expense generator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately there are ways to optimize depending on the situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can buy older cars in order to cut on the initial price. Usually a car, that's just a few years old, can cost
    20-30% less.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also buy vehicles which require much less operational costs in terms of fuel, maintenance and repairs.
    &lt;strong&gt;Diesel, hybrid and electrical vehicles can save a lot of money.&lt;/strong&gt; It's advisable to
    check when they'll pay back the initial investment and whether or not that's in sync with your plans.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When operating with a lot of cars proper vehicle management is crucial.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to maximize the utilisation of your vehicles, thus getting the most out of them. You don't want your cars
    sitting in a parking somewhere, that you pay for, if they can be making you money.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fleet management software can help a lot with this, alerting you whenever you need to change the oil or renew
    insurance, making proper usage schedules, etc.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;electric&quot;&gt;Save on the electric bill.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.erc-co.org/spooky-statistics-about-energy-and-water-waste/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;You
        won't believe how much energy
        is wasted every day&lt;/a&gt;, despite the fact that smart devices and &lt;a
        href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/jacobmorgan/2014/05/13/simple-explanation-internet-things-that-anyone-can-understand/&quot;
        target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;IoT&lt;/a&gt;
    have already entered our lives.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting fact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving the lights on in the office overnight &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.environment.admin.cam.ac.uk/facts-figures&quot;
                                                    target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;wastes
        enough energy to make 1000 cups of tea&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not to mention air conditioning, computers, etc. So integrating a smart system, that will turn off every device when
    it's not needed is a good way to save a lot of money.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to go one step further you can create more complex rules as to what is turned on or off and when.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some things you can do right away are:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Use led lights, they save a lot&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Use laptops instead of desktops, unless you really need the extra horsepower.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;If you're shopping for machines try to buy the ones with the highest efficiency rating, especially when it comes
        to heating or cooling.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Use high quality insulation for your office buildings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;inventory&quot;&gt;Don't keep excess inventory on hand.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It might seem like a good idea to be &quot;well stocked&quot; but it actually leads to a lot of excess expenditure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You'll have to pay for storage.&lt;/strong&gt; Depending on what you're storing and where you're storing it, this can be pretty
        expensive. Even if it's not, it's absolutely pointless to pay for
        something to just sit somewhere.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In some cases a new law or regulation might make a part of your stock unusable.&lt;/strong&gt; If you're producing food, a new
        law might make all your food dyes or packaging unusable. If you're
        dealing with air conditioners you might be left with lots of unusable coolant, that you even have to pay to
        dispose of. Even if things like these are out of your scope you might decide you
        want to change the design of your labels. How is that going to happen if you're sitting on a few hundred
        thousand ready ones?
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's what you can do instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invest in a good inventory management tool or module and do some inventory planning. You'll be able to create
    complicated schedules, to have statistics when you'll need more stock and when less and
    in general to predict what stock levels you'll need with great accuracy. It'll save you some cash and a lot of
    headaches.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
    This rule applies only to inventory or stock, e.g. assets you put in your production. If you have an asset you keep
    in order to sell for a higher price (investment asset), that's OK. Just make sure that the sale margin is bigger
    than what you paid to keep the asset.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;financial&quot;&gt;Financial cost saving&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/financial-cost-saving.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;How to save from finance services&quot;
     title=&quot;How to save from finance services&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you own a company, chances are - you are using financial services. Be it a bank account, money transfers,
    insurances, etc. All these services add up when you grow and can become expensive.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If your company is a big client of the finance sector you should always be trying to get a better deal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here's how:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check the prices that other financial service providers are offering.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pay special attention to companies that would want and would try to win you over. Usually they'll give the best
    possible terms.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are offered a better deal, contact your current provider and ask them to match those terms or even ask for
    better ones. If they don't do it, consider changing providers. This is a simple way to lower financial costs, that
    can be especially helpful for smaller businesses, where every dollar matters.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;fintech&quot;&gt;Use fintech services&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 my-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe class=&quot;embed-responsive-item&quot; data-src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/-EoNrg_DR3s&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The finance sector is changing rapidly due to the mainstream adoption of technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/fintech.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;new
        finance services&lt;/a&gt; emerging that could give you a lot more bang for your buck.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One good example are wire transfers, especially if currency conversion is involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional banks usually give you absurd conversion rates and pretty bad transfer fees. Instead you can use one of
    the many money transfer services (like &lt;a href=&quot;https://transferwise.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;
                                              rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;TransferWise&lt;/a&gt;) with pretty much no
    fees and with reasonable conversion rates. &lt;strong&gt;I can tell you from personal experience, that this is actually
    saving me a lot of expenses.&lt;/strong&gt; But more importantly it's a much more convenient and time-saving alternative.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you're using management software you can integrate payments in it. There are a lot of different
payment providers (like &lt;a href=&quot;https://stripe.com/&quot; title=&quot;Stripe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Stripe&lt;/a&gt; or
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paypal.com&quot; title=&quot;PayPal&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt;) making it possible to easily make
    payments from pretty much any application.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;unneeded-services&quot;&gt;Check if you really need all the services you are currently using.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have a couple of overlapping insurances, a bank account you rarely use or something else. Whatever the case
    try and monitor for such things and remove them as soon as you can. Your business management tool should be able to
    help you with things like this.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;late-payments&quot;&gt;Avoid late payments.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not as easy as it sounds, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could be waiting to be paid yourself or you could be receiving a ton of invoices on a monthly basis and you're
    simply forgetting about some of them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little bit of management software can help a lot here. You can have alerts for invoices that are about to be due,
    you can also plan ahead to avoid not having enough cash on hand at the moment and
    having to pay more later.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;marketing&quot;&gt;Marketing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;embed-responsive embed-responsive-16by9 my-4&quot;&gt;
    &lt;iframe class=&quot;embed-responsive-item&quot; data-src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/LUbqRwp8NXI&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like the finance sector, marketing is being revolutionized thanks to search engines, social networks, web forums
    and many other platforms that aggregate and show content in one way or another.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your business relies on advertisements to get new clients maybe you should shift your focus a bit to gain more for
    what you're paying. If done right digital marketing can have huge benefits, so
    maybe that TV or radio commercial that you're running and that's costing you an arm and a leg simply isn't worth it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital marketing has the benefits of reaching very specifically targeted audiences&lt;/strong&gt;, which are much more likely to
    buy. Also there's the benefit of being able to manage every aspect of your campaigns from your computer, which
    would save a lot of time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Another important part of marketing is giving your company's name the brand status.&lt;/strong&gt; This isn't easy to achieve, but
    digital marketing can help a lot. If you manage to do it, you'll gain big cuts in
    your advertisement expenses.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the easier steps to start walking towards the brand status are to post on specialized forums in order to show
    your expertise, maybe run a blog or post regularly in a magazine to gain more
    popularity, answer on platforms like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;quora&lt;/a&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In general digital marketing gives you much more bang for your buck.&lt;/em&gt; Thus helping in the reduction of
the expenses for advertisements.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;bad-cost-cutting&quot;&gt;Bad cost cutting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; data-src=&quot;/assets/img/posts/images/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide/bad-cost-cutting.jpg&quot;
     alt=&quot;There are also bad ways to cut costs&quot;
     title=&quot;There are also bad ways to cut costs&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here it is, as promised in the beginning of this post - bad ways to reduce costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number one rule of expenditure reduction is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You should never compromise the quality and value you provide to your customers and to your employees.
    &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually you can get away with a small drop in your services. Nobody is going to notice, right? Sadly in most cases
    that leads to more and more cuts being made and without even realising it you are
    on the track of rapidly losing your clients.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation with your employees is similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well because of this simple equation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unhappy employees = unhappy customers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cutting salaries or benefits, providing cheap tools or worse - not providing them at all and in general - reducing
    the quality of the working environment in any way are all perfect examples of bad
    ways to cut costs. They lead to bad quality and low value of the services or products you provide. Ultimately
    they'll make your clients search for an alternative.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a main takeaway from this section I'll give you a list of measures, that I consider really bad and
    in some cases desperate cost cutting techniques, that I think, shouldn't be used:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Lay offs, because employees are expensive. This was probably caused by hiring too much workforce in the first
        place or some other bad decision. Try not to do this, because it
        reduces morale, it damages your image and it's bad practice in general. However if you absolutely have to, then
        have meetings with the remaining employees and explain what is happening.
        Boosting morale in such situation is mandatory.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Don't cut on employee perks. Especially if they are highly valued. You'll simply piss off your workers and
        sooner or later you'll suffer the consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Don't save from what you give to your clients. From smaller meals, through cheap knock-off parts, to bad
        untested software it's all going to make you lose clients.
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Don't start from Marketing. In a crisis one should try to get more business, which translates to more marketing
        effort, not to less.
    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course there are more, but these aren't specific and apply to the majority of situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you made it this far, I want to thank you for being so patient. I hope you found this article useful and the tips
    helped you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'll be glad to &lt;a href=&quot;/contacts&quot;
                                   title=&quot;Contacts page&quot;&gt;answer&lt;/a&gt; any questions you might have or add
    things you think are relevant. Of course I'll try to keep this guide updated with new and relevant information.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Overall these are just some ideas on how to cut costs for your business.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on your core activity there are probably much more things you could do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main takeaway is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don't sacrifice quality and value to reduce your expenses. These are desperate measures and they don't work long
    term. Try to act in advance, before things start to go bad.&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
            <link>https://digidworks.com/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://digidworks.com/reduce-expenses-business-ultimate-guide</guid>
            
            <category>Small business</category>
            
            <category>Medium business</category>
            
            <category>Cost reduction strategy</category>
            
            <category>Management</category>
            
            
            <category>guides</category>
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The beginning of the Smart Notifier</title>
            <description>    &lt;p&gt;Just like many other small agencies, freelancers, freelancer groups, etc. we get part of our projects from freelancing platforms. Freelancing platforms are cool - they provide some level of
        protection for you, they are a shared marketplace for suitable gigs and you don't really need to put any money into digital marketing if you decide to only use them.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;Motivation for developing&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;There is one problem though - you need to be constantly on every platform at the same time hitting that refresh button to get the latest list of job posts. If you don't you're simply gonna be
        the 38th person to send a proposal, which the client probably won't even read. So it's of utmost importance to be pretty fast when you scan through jobs and send your terms to the client.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;What the app does&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;After a couple of weeks of doing this the stupid way (e.g. hitting that refresh button) we decided it's time to create a small tool to do this for us. And so the Smart Notifier was born.
        Right now that's a rather small project, probably with a ton of bugs and lacking in UI, but that's not a problem if you want to use it. It's based on Bootstrap 4, React.js and MobX for
        the client side and a tiny bit of PHP wrapped in Laravel for the server.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The purpose of the app is to be an auto refreshing list of job posts. Currently it only supports job posts from Upwork and Guru, but maybe we'll add more later if we see the need to or
    if a new, better platform arises.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The link to the GitHub repo is here -
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nikolai-tenev/smart-notifier-frontend&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;Front end github repo&quot;&gt;front end&lt;/a&gt;,
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nikolai-tenev/smart-notifier-backend&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;Back end github repo&quot;&gt;back end&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;How to use it&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;After installation and deployment on your PC or server, navigate to the URL of the notifier, click the filter button (the one in the middle) add the &lt;strong&gt;RSS Strings&lt;/strong&gt; for your
        queries and hit the
    refresh button. &lt;strong&gt;RSS Strings&lt;/strong&gt; are a part of the URL of the job list page on whichever platform. In Upwork you get it by going to your job feed or desired search,
    clicking the RSS button, choosing RSS and the copying the part from the URL starting after the &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; and ending before the &lt;code&gt;&amp;securityToken&lt;/code&gt;.
    In Guru you get the RSS string by going to job search, adding any desired filters and then copy everything in the address bar after &lt;code&gt;jobs/&lt;/code&gt; without the trailing slash in the end.
    If you have any problems - please feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;/contacts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; title=&quot;Contacts Page&quot;&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;Next steps&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Right now it's doing the job for us, so maybe we'll use it as is. If there's interest maybe we'll enhance it a bit. There's a problem though - using the RSS feeds has proven to be a bit of
    a problem, because both Guru and Upwork are trying to limit automated access to their platforms. Using API isn't really an option because Upwork's terms are ridiculous and Guru doesn't event have
    an API. So we're kinda limited, but still - it works, so happy freelancing!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
            <link>https://digidworks.com/the-beginning-of-the-smart-notifier</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://digidworks.com/the-beginning-of-the-smart-notifier</guid>
            
            <category>Bootstrap</category>
            
            <category>React.js</category>
            
            <category>Laravel</category>
            
            <category>Javascript</category>
            
            <category>HTML</category>
            
            <category>CSS</category>
            
            <category>PHP</category>
            
            
            <category>open-source-projects</category>
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Does your business need custom software?</title>
            <description>    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Problem with most people is - they don't see their problems&lt;/em&gt;. You are running small, medium or even a big company.
        Everything seems fine, you get decent income, your employees are happy and you have clients. It seems that there's no room for optimization, no way to make things better,
        but is this the reality or just a fool's paradise?&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Well, as it turns out lots of companies are living in the past. They refuse to embrace new technology solutions, that will make them agile and will help them save money.
        Here are 8 signs that will tell you if you can optimise your business processes by using custom-made software.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h4&gt;You don't automate anything&lt;/h4&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Probably one of the first needs ever solved by computers is optimising repetitive tasks. Software automation is fairly advanced nowadays and can save lots of man-hours, which saves money.
        If you find yourself doing the same thing or similar things (like invoices, payroll, inventory, etc.) over and over again, then custom software is probably one possible solution.
        Not only will you save time and therefore money, but more importantly you'll be able to avoid some small technical mistakes, that are easy to make otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h4&gt;Many apps for a single task&lt;/h4&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;So you have an e-commerce web app, through which you receive orders. But you also have an app for handling sales, another for shipping, one that bills, one that invoices, a time tracker for
        your employees of course, etc. etc. etc... oh and don't forget those Excel/Google Spreadsheets used as reporting tools. Sounds like a normal setup for most of the companies, right? Well,
        probably yes, but there's room for optimisation. All this can be done within the e-commerce web app you're already using and big part of the data input and the reports generating can be
        fully automated and a lot less error prone. Sounds good, right? All thanks to custom web development!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h4&gt;Many steps for a single action&lt;/h4&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;It's frustrating and inefficient to take multiple steps to complete a single action. General purpose ERPs, CRMs, and other management software try to be jack of all trades. Sadly they end up
        being master of none. With custom made business management software you're guaranteed to have your interface and functionalities tailored for your specific case.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h4&gt;More than one location&lt;/h4&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;If you operate in more than one office then communication is usually a problem. You will have to use flash drives or transfer files via e-mail and then compare, edit, etc. This is a cumbersome
        and error-prone process. But with a custom website or application you can avoid this and save yourself the trouble of synchronizing the data between offices.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h4&gt;Doing reports by hand&lt;/h4&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Back in the day everybody used Excel (or something similar) to create their reports. There were people filling tons of data into spreadsheets by hand, that generated reports. The more tech
        savvy used a database with complex queries to get the data and some visualization tool to generate the charts. Of course a single typo or any other simple error could mess up those reports
        quickly. Nowadays all the business intelligence, reports, analytics, etc. should be automated. This is easily achieved with tailor-made web app.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h4&gt;Lots of paper&lt;/h4&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;People should quit tobacco and businesses should quit paper!&lt;/em&gt; Going paperless means being environmentally friendly, cost effective and of course up-to-date. If you find yourself using
        tons of paper, constantly printing and scanning stuff, using O(ptical) C(haracter) R(ecognition) software to convert some of your documents to digital form, then it's probably time to switch.
        Custom software, tailored especially for you, will help you to drastically reduce the amounts of paper you use.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h4&gt;Hard to use apps&lt;/h4&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Not all apps are intuitive and easy to use. If doing something with your current software seems too hard and unnecessarily complicated - it probably is. However there's an alternative - you
        can get yourself some custom-made app with interfaces created according to your own wishes, granting you ease of use.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h4&gt;Paying too much for apps&lt;/h4&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Many people still think that custom-made software is way too expensive for them. This is actually a thing of the past. Nowadays most of the off the shelf software has exceptionally high
        licensing costs, monthly or yearly fees as well as installation and integration costs. If you do the calculation you'll find out that most of the times hiring an agency to create a
        specialized piece of software for you is actually way cheaper, than buying some commercial solution.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class=&quot;cta&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you see yourself in the situations described above and what do to something about it, that will help you to reduce costs, save time, make your processes less error prone,
            &lt;a class=&quot;highlight-dark&quot;
   href=&quot;/contacts&quot;
   title=&quot;Drop us a line on our contacts page&quot;&gt; go ahead and write us a few lines about it, we can help&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
            <link>https://digidworks.com/does-your-business-need-custom-software</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://digidworks.com/does-your-business-need-custom-software</guid>
            
            <category>Middle sized companies</category>
            
            <category>Small companies</category>
            
            <category>Management</category>
            
            
            <category>management</category>
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Adventures in the world of GitLab CI</title>
            <description>    &lt;p&gt;I start this article with an important disclaimer - I haven't used GitLab's continuous integration so far, so this post can be seen kind of as an intro.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;How does the whole thing work?&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In general, each repository is already connected with the GitLab CI system. The only thing that needs to be done in order to run the CI itself is to commit a &lt;code&gt;.gitlab-ci.yml&lt;/code&gt; file.
        This will cause a new CI job to be started on each subsequent commit.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The CI job is described in the &lt;code&gt;.gitlab-ci.yml&lt;/code&gt; file. Generally speaking it contains your chosen docker image and all the commands you want it to execute.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;One cool option, that GitLab gives you, is that you can enter names and values of variables in your account for later use in the &lt;code&gt;.gitlab-ci.yml&lt;/code&gt; file. This way your sensitive data
        will be protected from the public. At the time of writing, the variables are entered through Project -&gt; Settings -&gt; Pipelines -&gt; Secret Variables. The documentation of GitLab CI is
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gitlab.com/ce/ci/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot; title=&quot;GitLab CI docs&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;What exactly did I do?&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;In this first encounter with the CI implementation of GitLab I had a fairly simple task. On every single commit for a PHP and Laravel based project, the project had to be built, tested and
        deployed. According to different guides, documentation, etc. eventually I managed to do it with the following content in my &lt;code&gt;.gitlab-ci.yml&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;pre&gt;
        &lt;code&gt;
        image: edbizarro/gitlab-ci-pipeline-php:alpine

        before_script:
                - sudo apk --update add openssh-client
                - cd laravel
                - composer install
                - composer dump-autoload
                - php artisan clear-compiled
                - php artisan cache:clear
                - php artisan route:clear
                - php artisan view:clear
                - php artisan config:clear
                - cd ..
                - mkdir -p ~/.ssh
                - eval $(ssh-agent -s)
                - '[[ -f /.dockerenv ]] &amp;&amp; echo -e &quot;Host *\n\tStrictHostKeyChecking no\n\n\tServerAliveInterval 30\n\n\tServerAliveCountMax 6\n\n\tPort 1022\n\n&quot; &gt; ~/.ssh/config'

        deploy:
            script:
                - ssh-add &lt;(echo &quot;$MY_SSH_PRIVATE_KEY&quot;)
                - rsync -a -q -z /builds/GITLAB_ACC/REPO_NAME/some_laravel_dir/ USER_NAME@HOST_NAME:some_laravel_dir
                - rsync -a -q -z /builds/GITLAB_ACC/REPO_NAME/your_www_dir/ USER_NAME@HOST_NAME:your_www_dir
        &lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;/pre&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;Now a little explanation of what's what&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;With &lt;code&gt;image&lt;/code&gt;, you choose which docker image to use in the CI job. There are a lot of docker images available. You can find them either in Google or at https://hub.docker.com,
        or in some guide or documentation, where someone has recommended a cool image. It's very important to choose your image very carefully, because the different ones have different
        pre-installed software, scripts and configurations. There are a lot of images with very poor documentation that have insufficient information about what's inside the image.
        My recommendation is to use something popular, well documented and of course appropriate for the project. In the case of &lt;code&gt;edbizarro/gitlab-ci-pipeline-php:alpine&lt;/code&gt;,
        the cool thing is that I have everything I need pre-installed, including the php extensions. This means that I will not have to wait to install software and compile php extensions every
        time, which was actually the case with other images.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;before_script&lt;/code&gt; section is a list of preparatory steps that are executed before the task itself. A brief description of the steps in my case is:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;update sources list and install openssh-client&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;cd into the Laravel folder&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I run a bunch of composer and laravel artisan commands to set up the project&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;cd back into home folder&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I set up SSH settings - this is to remove the strict verification of the host key, to put an &lt;code&gt;alive interval&lt;/code&gt; and to set the preferred connection port&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;deploy&lt;/code&gt; part describes the CI task itself. The steps are:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I add my private ssh key&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I start the file upload&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;Difficulties that I encountered and how I overcame them&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I originally decided to upload via a ftp client, because for some weird reason I thought it would be better. Big mistake. Slow, difficult and problematic. I tried with lftp and ncftp.
        There was one pretty strange problem - not all directories and files were uploaded, only part of them, even though I used the recursive flag. I guess the problem was some kind of timeout
        or something, but I really had no desire to debug it, so I just went with SSH. This was way better. It's pretty fast, more secure and best of all - it works!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;GitLab surprised me, I was expecting a much worse free tier CI implementation. Aside from the problems I faced, which were entirely caused by my own ignorance, everything went well.
        Currently, with each commit the new version is directly deployed. This saves me a ton of time, because I don't have to do it myself. &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class=&quot;cta&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you find yourself on the lookout for more automation, that will help you accomplish your tasks faster and more efficient,
            &lt;a class=&quot;highlight-dark&quot;
   href=&quot;/contacts&quot;
   title=&quot;Drop us a line on our contacts page&quot;&gt; go ahead and write us a few lines about it, we can help&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
            <link>https://digidworks.com/adventures-in-the-world-of-gitlab-ci</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://digidworks.com/adventures-in-the-world-of-gitlab-ci</guid>
            
            <category>Laravel</category>
            
            <category>Docker</category>
            
            <category>CI/CD</category>
            
            <category>GitLab</category>
            
            <category>PHP</category>
            
            
            <category>devops</category>
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>How can a business benefit from IoT? [Examples]</title>
            <description>    &lt;p&gt;More and more devices are becoming &quot;smart&quot; and connected to the network. And by &quot;network&quot; I don't mean the electric grid, but the global information network. For example - who had heard about
        a &quot;smart&quot; watch a couple of years ago? Even they are no longer seen as something new. It is now up to other devices to get &quot;smarter&quot; and form the so-called Internet of Things.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;The Internet of Things is the network of interconnected devices (things) that can exchange data with each other, are connected to the internet and in short - they can be managed even from your
        phone. At first it sounds superfluous for the stove to have access to the web, but it's pretty cool to get home from work and be greeted by the aroma of a freshly baked roastbeef.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Of course, culinary is not the only application of these evolved devices - every small and medium business can benefit from them and here I am going to list some interesting applications.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;Smart bulbs&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Yes, those bulbs. And yes, with the Internet, why not? At present, many companies are producing the so-called smart bulbs. LED technology is used, which is nice because it reduces the
        electricity bill. So, what is the real benefit of a smart bulb?&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;Remote control&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;These bulbs can be controlled by a very large set of devices including phone, computer, a special remote and more. A lot of useful functionality especially for people who forget to turn off
        the lights when leaving a certain subject. There are patterns that allow automatic switching even when you are only a certain distance from them. You can also set a timer to determine when
        to turn it on and off.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;Wide range of colors.&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Most bulbs allow you to choose the color of your lighting.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Business Application: I've already mentioned the option to turn them off remotely if you have forgotten them, but that's not the only plus. Shop owners would benefit from being able to quickly
        and easily adjust the lights. Also the wide range of colors gives you an easy way to create an atmosphere. If you have a large room, you can set them to automatically turn on only in the area
        you are currently in.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;Smart alarms&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Alarm systems are not new. Also, they are usually connected in some way with some communication system to tell the guards about a potential problems. The bad thing is that they are amazingly
        stiff. Anyone, who has used such system, has activated it by mistake at least once, has wondered how to turn it on or off, has entered the wrong code until the guards show up, etc. Smart
        alarm systems solve these problems. Different systems are equipped with various sensors - vibration, infrared, temperature, motion, proximity, and more. After configuring the alarm, you start
        to receive notifications every time one of the sensors detects something you have defined as &quot;not normal&quot;. There are systems equipped with camera and/or speakers, that can help you see what's
        happening in real time, and startle the offender (or colleague :) ). Other systems offer small components
        (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.allbe1.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noreferrer noopener&quot;&gt;for example&lt;/a&gt;), again fitted with a large array of sensors, that you can use to track what you want
        (e.g. bicycle, laptop, dog, etc.) or let you know if the UV levels are too high.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Business Application: Generally, these alarms can be used for a lot of things - first of all their traditional function, but done in a much more convenient and elegant way, but also - to keep
        and track your personal belongings, to check who accesses your personal space such as rooms, drawers, etc., and even find your car in an underground parking.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h3&gt;Smart Button&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This is no longer a new thing, and yet it's pretty cool. It is a programmable button that connects to another smart device and sends commands when being pressed. There is an option to change
        the commands according to the type of press.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Business application: This thing should be present in every restaurant - short press calls the waiter, long press asks for the bill. The possibilities, of course, are not limited to
        this - with this button you can allow someone to have partial access to other clever things without being fully connected.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;h2&gt;Complete solutions&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;As a kind of a conclusion I want to mention probably the coolest aspect of the IoT devices - interconnection. What this means is you can connect everything with everything, creating pretty
        complicated systems, that can do a lot with the right software.
    If you really want to (or need to) you can make whole &quot;smart homes&quot;, &quot;smart offices&quot;, &quot;smart conference rooms&quot; or even hotels, buildings, etc. Only thing you need in addition to well designed
        IoT hardware is the software to monitor and manage it.
    &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p class=&quot;cta&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you find yourself in the need for functional and efficient management and monitoring system for your IoT devices,
            &lt;a class=&quot;highlight-dark&quot;
   href=&quot;/contacts&quot;
   title=&quot;Drop us a line on our contacts page&quot;&gt; go ahead and write us a few lines about it, we can help&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
            <link>https://digidworks.com/business-applications-of-iot</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://digidworks.com/business-applications-of-iot</guid>
            
            <category>Gadgets</category>
            
            <category>Internet of things</category>
            
            <category>Middle sized companies</category>
            
            <category>Small companies</category>
            
            <category>Management</category>
            
            
            <category>management</category>
            
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
